Guide to the Kellogg-Dickie Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kellogg-Dickie papers
1862-1995
1884-1976
MS 626
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
The Kellogg-Dickie Papers focus largely on Vernon and Charlotte Kellogg and their daughter, Jean Kellogg Dickie. The papers emphasize Charlotte and Vernon Kellogg's involvement in relief work for Poland and Belgium during and after World War I and Charlotte Kellogg's writings. Most of the Jean Kellogg Dickie material concerns her career as an artist and her involvement in the community.
Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jean Kellogg Dickie, 1970-1985; transfer from Acquisitions Dept., 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Files, 1891-1979. II. Writings and Creative Efforts, 1884-1967. III. Personal Papers, 1901-1995. IV. Photographs, 1862-1953.
Scope and Contents
The Kellogg-Dickie Papers document the civilian relief work done by Charlotte and Vernon Kellogg during and after World War I. They also relate to Charlotte Kellogg's research in connection with her books on Belgium and Poland. The papers include awards and newspaper clippings in connection with Belgian and Polish honors bestowed on the Kelloggs for their relief work. The Kellogg's major correspondents include Herbert Hoover, Ignace Jan Paderewski, and William Allen White. Additional correspondence and writings document the personal life and artistic career of Jean Kellogg Dickie. Her correspondents include Merle Armitage, a book designer and agent, who worked with James Dickie, and Robinson Jeffers, for whose book Jean Dickie created etchings.
Biographical / Historical
Vernon Lyman Kellogg, who was born in December 1, 1867 in Emporia, Kansas, earned both his B.A. in 1889 and his M.A. in 1892 at the University of Kansas, where he was assistant, then associate professor of entomology from 1890 to 1894. He continued his studies in biology at universities in Leipzig, Paris, the University of California, and Brown University, before completing his D. Sc. at Oberlin in 1922. From 1894 through 1920, he was professor of entomology and bionomics at Stanford University, but he took a leave for humanitarian work with American relief efforts in Europe during and after World War I. Herbert Hoover, a longtime friend, appointed him as the director of the Commission for the Relief in Belgium (CRB), where he served from 1915 to 1916. His wife, Charlotte, was the only woman member of the CRB before the U.S. intervention in the war.
Charlotte Hoffman, whom Vernon Kellogg married in Florence on April 27, 1908, was born in 1874, at Grand Island, Nebraska, of Swiss parents. She was a graduate of the University of California, earning a Ph.B. in 1900, and also studied abroad. For many years, she headed the English Department at Anna Head's School in Berkeley, California. She went to Brussels in 1916 during World War I by permission of the German government to join her husband and worked with the Comission for Relif in Belgium for a year. She was prominent in war relief work as a speaker and fund raiser.
Herbert Hoover appointed Vernon Kellogg as assistant to the U.S. Food Administrator. Kellogg was chief of the mission to Poland (1917-1919) and special investigator in Russia and other European countries with the American Relief Administrator (1918-1921). From 1919 to 1931, he was permanent secretary of the National Research Council, Washington, D.C., becoming secretary emeritus in 1933.
In 1921, Charlotte Kellogg was sent to Europe by President Harding to escort Marie Curie to the United States to receive a gram of radium and a special research grant. She directed the Paderewski Testimonial Fund for Polish relief and was involved in a Polish hospital that had been created in Edinburgh for the care of Polish refugees. She was decorated by France, Belgium and Poland for her service to those countries. She was the author of several books about Belgium and Poland. After Vernon Kellogg died on August 8, 1937, Charlotte Kellogg continued to live and write in California, where she died on May 8, 1960.
Charlotte and Vernon Kellogg had one daughter, Jean, who devoted her life to the arts. She studied for three years at the Yale School of Fine Arts and at the Art Students League in New York City and in Washington, D.C. She provided etchings for a book of poetry, The Loving Shepherdess, by Robinson Jeffers. Her work was shown in California and New York among other venues and later, she herself ran an art gallery in Monterey, California. She was married on July 31, 1960, to James Dickie, an artist who was known for his cartoons and for his books teaching children how to draw.
International relief; Reconstruction (1914-1939) -- Poland; World War, 1914-1918 -- Civilian relief; Belgium -- History -- German occupation, 1914-1918; Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975; Dickie, James; Dickie, Jean Kellogg; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Kellogg, Charlotte; Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941; White, William Allen, 1868-1944; Commission for Relief in Belgium
- General Files, 1891-1979; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is composed largely of correspondence but also includes some reports, clippings, and other materials associated with various subjects. The initial files include correspondence that is arranged chronologically. Among the files of particular correspondents are letters from Herbert Hoover, Ignace Paderewski, Robinson Jeffers, Marie Curie, Merle Armitage, and several publishers. The Paderewski files contain documentation of Charlotte Kellogg's leadership in raising money for Polish relief and her involvement in the the Paderewski Testimonial Fund, which helped purchase medical materials. Between 1917 and the 1930s, the correspondence is with both Vernon and Charlotte Kellogg. From the 1940s to the 1960s, it is largely Charlotte Kellogg's, with some belonging to Jean Kellogg Dickie. The later correspondence is Jean Kellogg Dickie's.
  - Chronological, 1917-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 11)
  - Alphabetical
    - Adams, Ansel, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adriani, Bruno, 1949-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Armitage, Merle, 1949-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 14 - 18)
    - Atlantic Monthly
      General
      See: Series I. General Files, 1891-1979 Folder 53
    - Barker, Eric, 1956-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Biddle, Mildred Barnes and Robert Wood, 1937-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Charlot, Jean C. and Zohmah, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Citron, Minna, 1960-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer, 1934-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Curie, Marie, 1921-1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Cutting, Olivia [Mrs. Bayard Cutting], 1938-1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Davis, Watson
      See: Series I. General Files, 1891-1979 Folder 52
    - Drew, Fraser B., 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Frost, Lesley, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Holmes, John and Sally, 1935-1948 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1915-1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hoover, Lou Henry [Mrs. Herbert Hoover], 1915-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Howell, Douglas, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Jeffers, Robinson and Una, 1934-1980 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Kellogg family, [1930]-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Krishnamurti, Jidou, 1941-1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Kusielewicz, Eugene, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Meyer, Agnes and Eugene, 1938-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Muir, John, 1907-1914 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Paderewski, Ignace Jan
      - General, 1930-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Clippings, 1925, 1932-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - National Paderewski Testimonial Fund, 1941-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 40 - 48)
    - Poor, Annie and Henry Varnum, 1939-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Ritchie, Ward, 1954-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Roosevelt, Nicholas, 1959, 1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Science Service, 1957-1967 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Sedgewick, Ellery, 1914-1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Silvercruys, Robert, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Sutcliff, Miss, 1891-1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Weston, Edward, 1941-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - White, William Allen, 1919-1943 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Unidentified, 1907, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Writing and Creative Efforts, 1884-1967; Series II
  This series contains articles and books with associated correspondence, notes, publicity blurbs, and reviews, related, for the most part, to Charlotte Kellogg's writings. Though Charlotte Kellogg's European relief work involved fund raising lectures, few of these are in the collection.
  The series includes materials concerning Charlotte Kellogg's Prelude, which describes her childhood and which was published posthumously by her daughter. A book and a few of Vernon Kellogg's articles are available, as is his 1884 ornithological notebook and a joint translation with his wife of Marie Curie's Pierre Curie. Jean Kellogg Dickie is represented here by an oral history and a lecture. The single example of James Dickie's work is a children's book.
  - Dickie, James: Your Child Can Draw, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Dickie, Jean Kellogg
    - The Loving Shepherdess [etchings]
      See: Oversize Folder 1
    - Oral history interview for Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Introduction of Lawrence Powell before his talk on Gordon Newell, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kellogg, Charlotte
    - General, 1917-1935, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      See also: Oversize Folder 12
    - Bobbins of Belgium, 1909-1959, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jadwiga of Poland, 1930-1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 6 - 7)
    - Jadwiga of Poland, 1930-1940, undated (Box 5, Folder 8 - 9)
    - Mercier, 1919-1920, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Pacific Light, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Paderewski, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Prelude, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Women of Belgium, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Kellogg, Vernon Lyman
    - General, 1902-1932 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Headquarters Nights, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Three Hundred Miles on the Colorado River [introduction], 1902
    - Ornithological notebook, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Kellogg, Vernon Lyman and Charlotte: Translation of Pierre Curie by Marie Curie, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Personal Papers, 1901-1995; Series III
  The awards, bibliographies, clippings, identification items, and memorabilia that comprise this series pertain to both Charlotte and Vernon Kellogg. Many of the awards attest to the humanitarian work of both Kelloggs during World War I. Materials for Jean Kellogg Dickie are found in her scrapbook. The scrapbook contains correspondence and clippings, with information about her personal life and artistic career, including brochures and reviews of her shows. There are interviews with political figures and artists, particularly those in the Monterey, California area where she opened an art gallery. The clippings often contain photographs of her. There are also articles about Charlotte Kellogg, including obituaries, in the scrapbook. Family items include a book written by Vernon's father, and another by his uncle. Memorabilia includes many books given and inscribed by friends and associates, several from their longtime friend, William Allen White.
  - Awards
    - Medals, 1914-1918, undated (Box 7)
    - Tributes and honors, 1918-1959, undated (Box 8, Folder 1 - 2)
      See also: Oversize Folder 10 See also: Oversize Folder 11
  - Bibliographies, 1914, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1914-1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Family, 1901-1947 (Box 8, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Identification documents: passports, visas, etc, 1918-1937 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Memorabilia
    - General, 1914-1940 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Books, 1901-1958 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook compiled by Jean Kellogg Dickie, 1936-1995, undated
    General note
    See: Oversize Folder 2 - 9
- Photographs, 1862-1953; Series IV
  This series contains portraits of Vernon and Charlotte Kellogg, as well as friends and associates, particularly Herbert and Lou Hoover, Ignace Paderewski, and a few family photographs. There are also postcards of sites in Belgium and Poland and photographs taken at the German General Headquarters in Brussels.
  - Kellogg, Charlotte, 1909-1945, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Kellogg, Vernon, 1916-1927, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Friends and associates
    - General, 1940-1953, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - De Marchienne, Emile de Cartier, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - General Headquarters of the German Army, [1915-1916?] (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Hoover, Herbert and Lou Henry, 1928, 1932-1933, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Howard, Sidney, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Jusserand, Jean Adrien Antoine Jules, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Mercier, Désiré [Cardinal Mercier], undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Meyer, Agnes, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Paderewski, Ignace J., 1862, 1875, 1921-1941, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - White, William Allen and Theodore Roosevelt, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Places
    - Belgium, [1913]-1921, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Poland, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Oversize
  - Dickie, Jean Kellogg
    - Etchings [ The Loving Shepherdess ], 1956 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbookand loose interleaved material, 1936-1995, undated (Box 11, Folder 2 - 9)
  - Kellogg, Charlotte
    - Award, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Banner, Les Amis des Belges, 1915 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Writings, 1919-1929 (Box 11, Folder 12)